Guide to Maurine Clow's Miss Montana Pageant Papers 1947-1968
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana--Missoula
Maurine Clow's Miss Montana Pageant Papers
1947-1968
University of Montana, Mansfield Library, Archives and Special Collections The University of Montana--Missoula Missoula, MT 59812 406-243-2053 http://www.lib.umt.edu/asc library.archives@umontana.edu
Mss 592
Clow, Maurine (1908-1986)
2.75 linear feet
The collection contains photographs, correspondence, clippings and miscellaneous materials related to the Miss Montana and Miss Montana State University (later The University of Montana) pageants.
Biographical Note
Maurine Clow was the longtime Associate Dean of Students at The University of Montana. She was born in Cavalier, North Dakota, in 1908. She had a bachelor’s and master’s degree in English literature and a Ph.D. in clinical psychology, all from Stanford University. She was Associate Dean of Women at Whitman College in Walla Walla, Washington, from 1939 to 1944. She served as The University of Montana Associate Dean of Students from 1946 until her retirement in 1973. She belonged to the Delta Gamma social sorority for over 50 years. She died in Missoula, Montana, in 1986.
Montana State University (now The University of Montana) took control over the Miss Montana Pageant in 1947, when the Associated Women students accepted the franchise to send their contestant to the Miss America Pageant in Atlantic City, New Jersey. In 1947, Carol Chaffin was selected as Miss Montana and went onto compete in the national competition. Dr. Maurine Clow coordinated the Miss Montana committees with the chairmen, contestants, and students. She was also Miss Montana’s chaperone to the Miss America Pageant.
The Miss Montana State University Pageant was first held in 1959. Its first winner was Patti Jo Shaw of Deer Lodge, Montana. Miss Montana State University winners went onto compete in the Miss Montana competition.
The collection contains photographs, correspondence, clippings and miscellaneous materials related to the Miss Montana and Miss Montana State University (later The University of Montana) pageants. The collection begins with a chronological arrangement of photographs and other materials related to individual women who were Miss Montana. What follows is a chronological arrangement of photographs and other materials from the Miss Montana Pageant itself and from Miss Montana’s participation in the Miss America Pageant in Atlantic City, New Jersey. The collection also contains materials from the Miss Montana State University Pageant and other University of Montana-related items. At the conclusion of the collection are pageant programs, two artifacts, and panoramic photographs and advertisements from the Miss America Pageant.
Materials have largely been arranged chronologically.
Researchers must use collection in accordance with the policies of Archives and Special Collections, the Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, and The University of Montana--Missoula.
Gift of Joan Hodgson, 1990
Negatives were physically removed from the collection for preservation.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
University of Montana--Missoula; Miss America Pageant; Miss Montana Pageant; Miss Montana State University Pageant
Beauty contests--Montana; Beauty contests--United States
Photographs
Montana; Women
Women deans (Education)--Montana--Missoula
- Carol Chaffin (Miss Montana 1947) and Miss America Pageant, photographs and clippings, 1947 and undated (Box-folder 1/1)
- Patti Luer (Miss Montana 1948), photographs and other materials (Box-folder 1/2)
- Patti Luer (Miss Montana 1948) and Miss America Pageant, photographs and other materials (Box-folder 1/3)
- Carol Fraser (Miss Montana 1949), photographs and other materials, 1949 and undated (Box-folder 1/4)
- Donna Buls (Miss Montana 1950), photographs and other materials, 1950 and undated (Box-folder 1/5)
- Patricia McGinty (Miss Montana 1951), clippings and correspondence, 1951-1953 (Box-folder 1/6)
- Patricia McGinty (Miss Montana 1951), photographs (Box-folder 1/7)
- Karen Whittet (Miss Montana 1952), photographs, 1952 and undated (Box-folder 1/8)
- Karen Whittet (Miss Montana 1952), clippings (Box-folder 1/9)
- Joanna Lester (Miss Montana 1961), photographs and other materials, 1960-1961 and undated (Box-folder 1/10)
- Miss Montana Program, 1948-1952 and undated (Box-folder 2/1)
- Miss Montana Pageant, miscellaneous, 1947-1951 and undated (Box-folder 2/2)
- Nancy Fields-Miss Montana Candidate, circa 1949 (Box-folder 2/3)
- Miss Montana Candidates, photographs, 1949-1950 (Box-folder 2/4)
- Miss Montana Pageant, 1951 (Box-folder 2/5)
- Miss Montana Pageant, photographs, 1951 (Box-folder 2/6)
- Miss Montana at Miss America Pageant, photographs, clippings, and writings, 1952 (Box-folder 2/7)
- Miss Montana, photographs, 1952 (Box-folder 2/8)
- Danny Lambros (Judges Committee Chair), correspondence, 1952 (Box-folder 2/9)
- [Miss Montana Candidates], photographs, undated (Box-folder 2/10)
- Miss America Pageant correspondence with Montana State University, 1946-1953 (Box-folder 2/11)
- Miss America Pageant, campaign and publicity correspondence (includes correspondence from Lenora Slaughter), 1947-1949 (Box-folder 2/12)
- Lenora Slaughter (Executive Director Miss America Pageant), correspondence, 1949-1960 (Box-folder 2/13)
- Miss America Pageant, photographs, 1951-1952 and undated (Box-folder 2/14)
- New York, New York-Atlantic City, New Jersey Expense, 1951-1952 (Box-folder 2/15)
- Miss America Pageant, Miss Montana float suggestions, 1951-1952 (Box-folder 2/16)
- Miss America Pageant programs and handbooks, memorabilia, 1946-1963 and undated (Box-folder 3/1)
- Miss America Pageant, photographs, 1952-1959, and undated (Box-folder 3/2)
- Miss Montana State University Pageant, photographs and clippings, 1961-1968 and undated (Box-folder 3/3)
- Miss Montana State University Candidates, photographs, 1962-1963 (Box-folder 3/4)
- Miss Montana State University Pageant, photographs, 1962 (Box-folder 3/5)
- Photographs [Miss Montana State University Pageant, 1962] (Box-folder 3/6)
- Photographs [Miss Montana State University Pageant, [1963] (Box-folder 3/7)
- University of Montana, miscellaneous, 1961-1972 and undated (Box-folder 3/8)
- Photographs [Miss University of Montana Pageant, [1967] (Box-folder 3/9)
- University of Montana, 1969-1970 and undated (Box-folder 3/10)
- Delta Gamma Sorority, 1953 and undated (Box-folder 3/11)
- Miscellaneous pageant winners and candidates, photographs, undated (Box-folder 3/12)
- Miscellaneous pageant clippings, 1947-1963 (Box-folder 3/13)
- Miss Montana Pageant Programs, [1949]-1967 (Box-folder 4/1)
- Miss America Pageant Programs, 1946-1967 (Box-folder 4/2)
- Miss University of Montana Programs, 1962-1967 (Box-folder 4/3)
- Handbook with notes about University of Montana student organizations, 1937-1949 (Box-folder 4/4)
- Publicity for Miss Clow’s speeches to groups, 1949-1950 (Box-folder 4/5)
- Junior Sponsors, photographs, undated (Box-folder 5/1)
- Junior Sponsors, 1971 and undated (Box-folder 5/2)
- “Dr. Maurine Clow, Local Pageant Director,” pin, undated (Box 6)
- Montana bison copper keychain related to Miss Montana Pageant, undated (Box 6)
- 3 rolled panoramic Catalina Swimsuit Advertisements at Miss America Pageant, undated (Box 6)
- Negatives (Box 6)
  Miss Montana State University Pageant Formal Groups, 1961
  Miss Montana State University Pageant, 1961
  Miss Montana State University Groups at Theta House, 1961
  Miss Montana State University Pageant, 1964